Okay, today's דף daf is פ״ט, pey tes, we have a little
bit to go to end the last פרק perek and then we
start the penultimate פרק. perek. We are about two weeks from the
finish line. So, going back and beginning from פ״ח עמוד ב׳ pe-ches
amud beis from the two dots. Basically we had been talking about
that if you pour water into your yard, your courtyard, if it's
four by four אמות, amot, then that's okay, but smaller than that
then it'll run off. There's a concern that it'll look like you're
intending, or you will intend, it'll look like you're intending it'll run
off into the רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, look like you're pouring straight
into רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, and therefore what we required was that
you make a pit that the water can go into. Now the
משנה mishna ended by saying that if you have two, you know,
second story buildings, two balconies that overlook a yard and one of
them had made a pit and the other had not, then only
the balcony that had made the pit can pour into the yard,
not the upper one.
Now, here I've just drawn you the scenario,
right, here you have your one, here you have the other, the
balconies. Here's the yard, this guy has made a pit, you know,
for him, for him, so he can go ahead and pour in,
and this guy cannot pour in. Now, on the face of it,
it's like, oh okay, sure, one guy has a pit, one guy
doesn't, but on the other hand, it's all the same yard, and
we just said that if a yard has a pit you can
use the yard, right? So, okay, so the yard has a pit,
so who cares if let's say the pit is nearer to this
guy or he's the one that made it? Why can't that guy
use the pit as well and pour water into the yard? I
mean there's a pit in the yard. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says about this. Okay, so it says, אמר רבא וכן
שתי דיוטאות, Amar Rava v'chein shtei diyutos, two like balconies, זו כנגד
זו. zo k'neged zo.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, four lines from the bottom on פ״ח עמוד
ב׳, pe-ches amud beis, says רבא, Rava, אפילו עירבו, afilu ervu, even
if they made an עירוב. eruv. So what the גמרא's Gemara going
to introduce as the problem there is that the reason one guy
can use it and the other can't is because since they've got
these two balconies, they are basically two owners of the yard, two
houses in the yard, right? And if you want me to draw
on flat, you basically have like this. You know, you have house
one, right, and house two, and it's a חצר. chatzer. And what
do you need to do with a חצר? chatzer? You have to
make an עירוב. eruv. And this guy has the pit.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to say that one way of
understanding the problem, or at least what's going to include is a
way of understanding the problem, is that the problem is that
if they haven't made an עירוב. eruv. I will get to רבא
Rava in a minute, but I'm telling you what the גמרא Gemara
is going to conclude. The situation is that they haven't made an
עירוב. eruv. So, they haven't made an עירוב, eruv, this is the
way the I'm going to jump to the way the גמרא Gemara
is going to conclude so you can sort of see more easily
how it's going to get there. They haven't made an עירוב, eruv,
neither of them can actually go down off of their balcony and
actually use the yard, bring stuff from their home into the yard.
So what you're afraid the guy's going to do is, if you
have to use the pit, you're going to take your chamber pot
or whatever it is, go into the yard and pour this stuff
into the hole. And they haven't made an עירוב eruv and that's
a concern. So why do we let this guy use it? Because
for this guy it's assumed presumably it's like right near his place.
So what he can do is he can basically spill his waste
onto his rooftop onto his balcony and it'll run off and it'll
go into the yard. And that apparently is allowed. That since he
is not directly moving stuff into the yard, right, that's what you
can't do without an עירוב, eruv, go from your house into the
yard. What he's doing is he's just pouring it on his balcony
and then it runs off, that's okay. But this guy isn't going
to can't do that because it's too far away. Okay, so this
guy, if we're going to let him do this, he's going to
have to walk out of his house and walk here and then
he's going to carry in the yard. So that's the way in
the end אביי Abaye is going to say is the issue. The
issue is they haven't had an עירוב, eruv, nobody can go directly
into the yard to use this, but the guy who can use
it is the guy who it's nearby because he can pour on
his balcony it can run off, we don't let this guy do
it even by pouring on his balcony because it's more likely once
we let him do it he'll come and carry in the yard.
Okay, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to conclude and that
it's an עירוב eruv problem. But רבא Rava starts by saying even
if they have an עירוב, eruv, he thinks that this is an
issue. אביי Abaye is not going to understand what's bothering רבא. Rava.
So אמר רבא אפילו עירבו, Amar Rava afilu ervu, even if they
made an עירוב. eruv. אמר אביי מאי טעמא, Amar Abaye mai ta’ama,
what's the reason that that's a problem? אילימא משום דאידמי, ileima mishum
d’idme,
maybe אביי Abaye says what's bothering you רבא Rava is that if
there are two houses and the yard is less than four by
four, so maybe when did we allow
less than four by four with a pit? When maybe it's one
house. Okay, but remember we made this point that we never spoke
about how many people are using the yard, right? The whole concern
is there's too much water and you need it to absorb, so
you make a pit, but how many people are using? Is it
one person using or a hundred people using the yard? So אביי
Abaye says maybe רבא... Rava... רבא *Rava* what you're saying is that
you got this small yard, less than four by four and we're
allowing it with a pit, maybe as soon as there's more than
one house in the yard, there are too many people using it
and we won't allow it. Of course if that was the issue,
it wouldn't explain why we let one guy use it and not
the other, then nobody should be able to use it. Okay, but
that's how אביי Abaye *Abaye* is interpreting what's bothering רבא *Rava*. Maybe,
okay, אילימא משום נפישא דמיא *eileima mishum nefisha demaya*, there's too much
water because you got two guys using the yard. והתניא *ve-hatanya*, but
that's not true, that is actually not a concern. Once you satisfy
our quantitative criteria, we don't ask about the actual reality of how
many people are using the yard. אחד עוקה *achad uka* ואחד גסטרא
ברכה ועריבה *ve-achad gistera breicha va-areiva*, whether or these other types of
sort of holes which are like larger various—a גסטרא *gistera* is actually
a pottery vessel. So you actually pour the water directly into a
chamber pot in the yard. Okay, or other types of furrows and
other things, or עריבה *areiva* kneading trough, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it's
a little like shaped like a boat. But whatever it is, whether
it's things underground or above ground, you can use all of these
things if your yard is too small. And here's the key line:
אף על פי שנתמלאו מים מערב שבת, Shabbos שופכין לתוכו מים בשבת
*af al pi she-nitmalu mayim me-erev shabbat, shofchin letocho mayim be-shabbat*. Even
if they were already filled from ערב שבת Shabbos *erev shabbat*, that
is legitimate. So presumably what אביי Abaye *Abaye* is saying is, we
see from there, once you satisfy the criteria of having a hole
or having a chamber pot, then we don't actually ask can it
really contain the water. Even if it's full and it can't really
contain any new water, well, technically
you've got your ditch, that's okay. So if that's true when it's
full, he says logically it should be true even if you have
ten people using the yard. Okay, so that's and the other thing
you could add is, if the problem in the משנה Mishnah. *mishnah*
was that there were too many people using the yard, you wouldn't
be able to understand why we allow
one guy and not the other. But presumably what רבא *Rava* is
saying is,
look, you have two people using the yard, it's a small yard,
all you have is the ditch, we only allow the ditch for
one person. So therefore, rather than saying they both can't use it,
we'll allow the ditch to be used for this one guy, and
therefore it'll be only a yard used by one guy and then
the ditch will be okay. That's presumably how רבא *Rava* read the
problem. רבא *Rava* read the problem, the problem was too many people
were using the yard. So therefore, we could say everybody can't use
it, but really we don't have to say that, we can say
only one person can use it, and then we're back to being
okay if the ditch only works for one person. So we're going
to give it to the guy who actually made the ditch. That's
presumably how רבא *Rava* read it. אביי Abaye *Abaye* says, I'm sorry,
once you've got the ditch, there could be ten people using the
yard. It doesn't really matter how practical it will be or not.
So therefore for אביי Abaye *Abaye*, the problem is going to be
the concern of עירוב eruv. *eiruv*, not the concern about too many
people using the ditch. אלא אי אתמר הכי אתמר *ela i itmar
hachi itmar*, here's how it was said, and actually it becomes a
re-read of רבא *Rava*. אמר רבא *amar rava*, לא שנו אלא שלא
עירבו *lo shanu ela shelo eirvu*.
The only problem of the guy who didn't use the ditch using
it is that there's no עירוב eruv. *eiruv*. And we're concerned that
because the ditch isn't near him, he's going to like I said,
carry into the yard. And the other guy won't carry, he'll just
pour and the water will run off. אבל עירבו מותרין *aval eirvu
mutarin*, but if they made an עירוב eruv? *eiruv* they both can
use it. And even though it's only one ditch for two guys,
we're not concerned with that. וכי לא עירבו *ve-chi lo eirvu* says
the גמרא Gemara *gemara*, מאי טעמא mai taama, לאו *mai ta'ama lav*?
And without an עירוב eruv, *eiruv*, what's the reason? אמר רב Rav
אשי *amar rav ashi*, גזירה דילמא אתי לאפוקי ממאני דבתים להתם *gezeira
dilma ati l'apukei mimani debatim lehatam*. We're afraid the guy who did
not make the ditch and is further away from will actually take
his chamber pots out to the ditch and then he'll be carrying
in the חצר chatzer, *chatzer*. Okay. הדרן עלך כיצד משתתפין *hadran alach
keitzad mishtatfin*. That is the end of that פרק perek. *perek* and
all those discussions about making מחיצות mechitzot. *mechitzot* to draw from balconies
over water and getting rid of waste water and various types of
leniencies and various types of concerns. Now we turn to, as I
said, the penultimate פרק perek *perek*, which is the one that's going
to finish up these discussions about what is considered various domains that
you can carry in based on whether you do or don't have
an עירוב eruv. *eiruv*. Yes.
So I've always been really careful about making sure that water doesn't
ever fall on the ground. It sounds from the גמרא Gemara *gemara*
that we're more lenient on that.
Yeah, I mean it's actually an interesting point as well. I mean
even when you're dealing with a מלאכה דאורייתא *melacha de-oreita*, for example
about זורע *zoreia*,
you can actually—this is relevant if people now that it's getting to
be the summer, people are having little picnics or whatever in their
backyard on שבת Shabbos, *shabbat*. And you want to do נטילת ידים
*netilat yadayim* or something like that. Actually if you pour the water
over the concrete and from there it runs off into the grass,
it's actually not a problem,
as long as you're in an עירוב eruv?
*eiruv*, which you always are with your עירוב eruv. *eiruv*. Then normally
by the way by גרמא *grama*, by מלאכות *melachot*, we assume that
it's
אסור assur *assur*, unless
you have at least it's אסור דרבנן *assur de-rabbanan* and you need
some justifying reason and so on. But specifically by this case of
גרם השקאה *gram hashka'ah*, actually we פוסקין *poskin* that that's actually straight
מותר *muttar*. So I mean not if you're intending for it, you're
not intending for it, but you're just washing your hands over the
concrete. This is a case also about you're right about going from
one רשות reshus *reshut* to another, but it's again תוספות *tosafot* discusses
it, it would not necessarily be the same going from let's say
a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *reshut ha-yachid* to a כרמלית *karmelit*. Here
you're going from a רשות reshus *reshut*. Here you're going from a
רשות, reshus. a house, into a חצר שאינה מעורבת, chatzer she-aina me-ureves,
which is really a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, just doesn't have an
עירוב. eruv? So in that case we're lenient when you, you know,
when it's indirect and it runs off. But basically there are definitely
some leniencies about this that we saw there at the end. Okay
let's take a look now at the next פרק. כל הגגות kol
ha-gagos
is here רשות אחת. reshus achas. So now what we are going
to be discussing is, and this has come up before and this
is the sort of focused discussion of it. Let's assume you haven't
made an עירוב. eruv, What's the consequence of not making an עירוב?
eruv. And by that I do not mean a צורת הפתח tzuras
ha-pesach that turns it into a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, what we
colloquially call עירוב, eruv but here you have your courtyard, okay, and
here you have all of your units, right, and you did not
make an עירוב. eruv What do you now not allowed to do
because you did not make an עירוב?
eruv Well you're not allowed to, if it was, forgetting stuff that
already was in the חצר, chatzer, but you can't take out...
Okay you can't take stuff from your house into the courtyard and
you can't take stuff from the courtyard into any house and therefore
you also can't take from one house into the other because you'd
go through the courtyard but even if you wouldn't, even let's say
or attached houses, right, you can't take from one house into the
other because they're different domains. Okay so you can't basically go from
one רשות reshus. to another and the רשויות reshuyos are, you know,
all of these things are different רשויות, reshuyos, are differently owned and
then this is a shared רשות reshus and so on and you
can't go from one to the other. But you can go, you
can carry stuff within your house and if it starts in the
חצר, chatzer okay it's where it starts, that gives it its identity.
If it started in the חצר chatzer. then you can carry it
throughout the חצר. chatzer. If it started in the house and you
transgressed and you brought it out, I'm not allowed to now take
it and move it in the חצר. chatzer. It still is a
your house's object and therefore your house's object cannot be moved in
the חצר. chatzer But something that is, but the object is identified
by where it was when שבת starts and that's the domain it
can stay in even without an עירוב.
eruv Why can you move it from the חצר chatzer into a
house?
You can't. You can move it, no, you can move it from
the חצר chatzer. within the חצר. chatzer, You can't just... that's okay.
You can't go into a house.
Even though there's no עירוב?
eruv, Even though there's no עירוב, eruv, it's a רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid. okay, it's a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. You've got your לחי
lechi or קורה, korah, it's a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid So the
only הלכה halacha is that you can't go from, you know,
from one domain to the next. Okay and again the domain is,
it's not just where you are right now, it's where the object
was identified when שבת begins. So if it started here then I
can't move it to any other place. Started here I can move
it within the courtyard, can't move it. If it started here and
I brought it out of the courtyard on שבת, it still relates
to this house and I can't move it in the courtyard. Okay
so that's the basic הלכה halacha if you don't have an עירוב.
eruv, So now what we're going to discuss is let's say you
have multiple courtyards, okay, and they open into one another and they
didn't make, this guy didn't make an עירוב eruv amongst themselves or
even if they did they didn't make an עירוב eiruv together with
this courtyard. Can I take from one courtyard and bring it into
the next? Okay are all the courtyards even without an עירוב eiruv,
considered essentially one domain? Okay and then from there to there. Now
you might say how is that different than like one house to
the next house? Right I told you even if they were connected
houses you can't. But the thinking would be that since these are
used less than the houses, houses really are the primary place you
use your objects. And therefore it's like this object, you know, therefore
there's a greater sense of it like being a different house, a
different space. Since this somehow is used less maybe we can all
say that you know what, we'll consider all the courtyards one domain
and if it starts in a courtyard even without an עירוב eiruv
it can move to other courtyards. That's the question. Okay so no
עירוב, eiruv, what anyway would be considered one domain so if an
object starts there it can be moved the same way within a
courtyard from courtyard to courtyard. Or what we're going to start with
now, which is why it's called כל הגגות, kol ha-gagos, its rooftops.
So here you have a couple of connected houses, okay, they have
not made an עירוב, eiruv so you cannot go from one house
to the next, right, but an object starts on the rooftop.
So maybe since the rooftop is not the same as a house
and since certainly from the top it's not obvious that it's a
different type of a domain either, maybe we'll consider all rooftops one
domain and say that if it starts on a rooftop you can
move it between the rooftops. So that is the focus of the
question. There is no עירוב, eiruv. what anyway would be one domain
that you can move it within that.
I mean if you were like you know on top of my
rooftop wouldn't that be trespassing, A, and then B...
Hey let's say I allow you. It's accepted, whatever. That's a separate,
that's a חושן משפט Choshen Mishpat question. Yeah.
Regarding the stuff in the חצר, chatzer. I mean I can understand
if maybe it's you know something that's usually in a house. But
let's say it's like a lawn chair, you're only going to use
in the חצר. chatzer So you're saying that even though the חצר
chatzer, is used less but this is only used in the חצר,
chatzer there
wouldn't be a problem saying... Right, yeah, but still חזל Chazal would
not have seen that, and that's the question, as much of a
boundary breaking, you know, because than the house case. I do understand
the point but that's the
question. Yeah, we quoted this משנה Mishnah *mishna*. This משנה Mishnah, *mishna*
was quoted in that discussion about when they forgot the מילה *milah*
knife and how they could commit. Yes, and that was exactly applying
the discussions of this משנה Mishnah. *mishna*. So let's take a look
at the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, okay? It says: כל הגגות עיר רשות
אחת *Kol ha-gaghot ir reshut achat*—all of the rooftops are one domain—ובלבד
שלא יהא גג gag, גבוה עשרה או נמוך עשרה *u-vilvad shelo yehei
gag gavo'ah asarah o namuch asarah*—as long as when going from one
roof to the next, it's not ten higher or ten lower. That
would actually define it at a different type of a domain. Now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to discuss why. Since... no, from
the other one. Higher or lower from the other one. Okay, they're
not separated from one another by a height of ten. That would
make it different. But the point is, a roof is anyway a
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, *reshut hayachid*, so who cares because of the
walls below, so who cares if you have a high רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid *reshut hayachid* or a lower one? But anyway, we'll see.
דברי רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Divrei Rabbi Meir*. That's what Rabbi Meir
says. וחכמים V'chachamim אומרים כל אחד ואחד רשות בפני עצמו *Va-Chachamim omrim
kol echad ve-echad reshut bifnei atzmo*. The Rabbis don't buy into it.
They say even all the rooftops are considered separate and you can't
go from one rooftop to another. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon אומר *Rabbi
Shimon omer*—now Rabbi Shimon is the most lenient—he says אחת גגות gagos
ואחת חצרות chatzeiros ואחת קרפיפות *achat gaghot ve-achat chatzerot ve-achat karpifot*, whether
rooftops or courtyards or קרפיפות *karpifot* which are like lots with, you
know, with a fence around them, רשות אחת הן *reshut achat hen*—they
are all one domain—לכלים ששבתו לתוכן *le-keilim she-shavtu letokan* and this is
what I was telling you, for vessels that started in there, ולא
לכלים ששבתו בתוך הבית *ve-lo le-keilim she-shavtu betoch habayit*, but not for
vessels that started in the house. So if vessels started in the
house, you can't take it to the courtyard and even if you
accidentally took it to the courtyard, you're no longer allowed to move
it within the courtyard. But for vessels that started in the courtyard,
you can go from one courtyard to the next. Now he said
courtyards, rooftops, and yards and like lots are all one domain. Now
the key question is how do you read all one domain? All
one domain respectively or all one domain all together? Meaning, is he
saying that you can take from lot to lot to lot or
roof to roof to roof or courtyard to courtyard to courtyard,
but what about from courtyard to a roof or from a courtyard
to a roof to a lot? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually
reads him in the most lenient way and says that they are
all one single domain. They are all spaces that are רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid *reshut hayachid* and they're not homes. Homes are places which
are much more, sort of, distinct, you know, in their identity and
the things that are in the homes. And there, those are distinct
domains. Homes are distinct from one another and distinct from all of
this. But all these more general spaces which are technically רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid, *reshut hayachid* are all considered the same category, the same
genre. So according to him, if I started something in my courtyard,
I could take it to another courtyard and then here if there's,
let's say, a ladder up on this roof, you know, because I
can't go into the house, right? I could go ahead and take
it onto the roof and then I can go down from that
roof and take it here into this קרפף karpaf. *karpef*, okay, all
of that is okay and from that to another קרפף karpaf, *karpef*
I can do all of that movement because it's all רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid *reshut hayachid* and these are all considered to be non-home
spaces which essentially are one and don't need an עירוב eiruv. *eiruv*
if you're moving from within those. But once it was started in
the home, you can't move it anywhere else even if you did
take it out, you're not allowed to continue to move it. Okay?
So that's what Rabbi Shimon says, it's all one. The תנא קמא
*Tanna Kamma* only said all the rooftops are one. We don't know,
would he say all the yards are one separate from the rooftops?
Okay, but that is the three-way debate. And the חכמים Chachamim. *Chachamim*
don't buy into any of this. Alright, so let's take a look.
So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. It says, יתיב אביי Abaye
בר אבין ורבי חנינא בר אבין ויתיב אביי Abaye גבייהו
*Yativ Abaye bar Avin ve-Rabbi Chanina bar Avin ve-yativ Abaye gabaihu*. Abaye
bar Avin and Rabbi Chanina bar Avin, these two sons of Rav
Avin were sitting and Abaye was with them. ויתבי וקאמרי *Ve-yatvi ve-ka'amri*,
and they were saying:
בשלמא רבנן סברי *Bishlama Rabbanan savri*—I get the Rabbis—they hold כשם שדיורן
חלוקין למטה כך דיורן חלוקין למעלה *keshem she-diyuran chalukin
lemata kach diyuran chalukin lemala*. The same way in the homes themselves
they're considered different domains, there are different inhabitants of it, so, you
know, House A is distinct from House B and it's a different
רשות *reshut*. So the rooftops as well follow the homes below and
Roof A is different from Roof B. אלא רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir,
*Ela Rabbi Meir*—but Rabbi Meir who says you can go from one
rooftop to another—מאי קסבר *mai kasavar*? What does he hold? אי קסבר
כשם שדיורן חלוקין למטה כך דיורן חלוקין למעלה *Ei kasavar keshem she-diyuran
chalukin lemata kach diyuran chalukin lemala*—if he agrees that the rooftops are
separate domains, so that can't be—אמאי רשות אחת הן *amai reshut achat
hen*? Why can you go from one rooftop to the next?
Carry—we're not talking about walking—carry. ואי קסבר אין חלוקין *Ve-ei kasavar ein
chalukin*—and if he holds, which is the obvious answer, that all... that
above, you know, when you're not in the house, when you're above
the house, it's all in a separate space and we don't consider
it to be sort of separate domiciles, particularly because nobody is living
on the roof. You understand, it's not just how high it is.
If people were living on the roof, then that would make different
domains. But nobody lives on the roof. So ואי קסבר אין חלוקין
*ve-ei kasavar ein chalukin*—they're not distinguished one from the other, the roofs—דכל
למעלה מעשרה רשות *de-kol lemala me-asarah reshut*. רשות אחת היא because it's
A, it's above ten, and B, what you have to add is
nobody actually lives there. So the combination of those two mean that
it's all considered like one domain. So if that's true, why does
he care that one rooftop is higher than ten from the other?
אפילו גג גבוה עשרה ונמוך עשרה נמי. afilu gag gavo'ah asara ve-namuch
asara nami. What's the basis of saying, "Oh, but if it's a
ten higher or lower than its other roof, then that makes it
separate"? What's the basis of being separate? You don't consider it that
they're separate—it's not the fact that there's separate people that use it
or live in it. That's not the distinguishing thing. So why should
just this difference of height make it separate? So the גמרא Gemara
says, here's why. אמר לה אביי, amar leh Abaye, אביי Abaye said
back to them, לא שמיע לכו הא דאמר רבי יצחק בר אדימי?
lo shemi'a lechu ha d'amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Adimi? Did you not
hear what רבי יצחק בר אדימי Rabbi Yitzchak bar Adimi said? אמר
היה רבי מאיר, amar haya Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used
to say, and same רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, כל מקום שאתה מוצא
שתי רשויות, kol makom she-atah motze shtei reshuyot, if you have two
domains, which doesn't mean any two domains, which really means, as we're
gonna see, a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid in a
רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid. כגון עמוד ברשות היחיד גבוה עשרה ורחב ארבע.
kegon amud bi-reshut hayachid gavo'ah asara ve-rachav arba. You have again this
pillar in רשות היחיד reshut hayachid that's ten high and four wide.
So it's a, the pillar is a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid itself.
Okay?
So what you've got here is,
you've got your simply, you've got your רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid okay?
And in the middle of רשות היחיד reshut hayachid you have a
pillar and the pillar even if it were in רשות הרבים reshut
harabim would be a, would be a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. because
it's ten by four. Okay? So that's your scenario, you've got your
pillar in that רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid, Okay? So what's the relevance
going to be? What is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir going to say?
So he says, אסור לקטף עליו, asur le-katef alav,
you cannot put stuff, shoulders, like take off your shoulder, you cannot
put stuff from the רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. onto the pillar. גזירה
משום תל ברשות הרבים, gezeira mishum tel bi-reshut harabim,
because then you'll think that you can put on this type of
a pillar even if it's in the middle of the רשות הרבים.
reshut harabim. So this is a crazy חומרא, chumra, right? This is
basically saying, I mean first of all we have to assume it
doesn't apply indoors, okay? Because then if it applied indoors like, what?
I can't put stuff on a table? Although table, you know, doesn't
have the stuff going down. I can't put stuff on a סטענדער?
shtender? I can't put stuff on top of my dresser? Okay? So
obviously we have to assume it doesn't apply indoors. But outdoors, okay,
he says you cannot put stuff even if you're in a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid. on like a pillar that is itself רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid, because you would come to then do the same thing
if such a type of a pillar or rock or whatever is
in the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Okay, now that again, the גמרא
Gemara is going to qualify that because even to say it outdoors
seems a little extreme. I mean, you know, you can't, in your
backyard you can't put stuff on your doghouse? I mean imagine that
we, what's that? We have the whole עירוב around, you know, whenever
we have it. Imagine we were to פסק'ן paskin this? So we
would have to be outside every time we're outside, don't put stuff
on like, you know, on like, you know, on pillars or whatever.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to try to qualify it but
assuming that's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir what the גמרא Gemara is using
to explain now is that if you have these different rooftops, it
makes it a very trivial, not trivial I should say but a
side point. You have these rooftops and this roof is, not doing
my three-dimensions well, but anyway, but this roof is עשרה טפחים asara
tefachim higher than that is basically this scenario. You are in a
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and therefore you can't put something onto that,
onto that higher roof because that's like the pillar that's in the
middle of your רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Okay? It doesn't sound like
that at all in the משנה. The משנה sounds like, "Look, once
it's ten high, we can't call it all the same essen—essentially the
same space, right?" It's not easily accessible one to the other, that
makes it a distinct space, even though it's already higher than ten.
Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is bothered because normally once stuff is
higher than ten we don't make distinctions between higher than higher than
ten. And therefore what makes this a different space? According to the
גמרא Gemara it's based on a side issue of רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir. of that you'll come to confuse it with putting stuff on
top of a pillar in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Yes?
But he doesn't prohibit putting it on a מקום פטור, makom patur,
which is almost the same thing?
But that wouldn't immediately be a violation. If this pillar were in
a רשות הרבים reshut harabim then you would have immediately transgressed. So
let's see, let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with
this. Okay. הכי נמי, hachi nami, here too, גזירה משום תל ברשות
הרבים, gezeira mishum tel bi-reshut harabim, we don't let you go from
a lower roof to a higher roof because it'll lead to this
case of putting stuff on a pillar in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
סברו מינה, sevaru minah, so when we heard that, they, when they
initially heard this idea about this, this putting it on a pillar,
we assumed אפילו מכתשת ואפילו גיגית, afilu machteshet ve-afilu gigis, even if
you have like a, you know, a, what do you call it,
a, what's a מכתשת? machteshet?
What? Yeah, mortar? Or even a, you know, or even like a
barrel. So you know, like I said, like you've got, I don't
know, you've got some type of a box out in רשות היחיד,
reshus hayachid. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir, wouldn't let you put something on
top of your box. He wouldn't let you put something on top
of
a
barrel. No, no, no, no, no, no, even when I'm saying this,
it doesn't mean like in all those cases, that would be crazy.
הכי אמר מר, hachi amar mar, here's what the master said, meaning
presumably the tradition of explaining רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir, לא אמר רבי
מאיר אלא עמוד ואמתא דריחיים. lo amar Rebbi Meir ela amud va-amasa
de-rechayim. He only said it by something that really is like a
more fixed, exact, you know, topography. So it's like you've got actually
a pillar or you have the אמת הריחיים amas harachayim which is
the big, you know, sort of the whole big configuration that they
make if you've ever seen these ancient oil presses in Israel, you
know, for the millstone, so it's a real part of like the
structure of the ground. Fixed. What? They've got a picture. I'm sure
they do. הואיל ואדם קובע להם מקום, ho'il v'adam koveia lahem makom,
because a person fixes a space. Okay. And again, I would say
I hope he's not saying it indoors also. I hope he's only
saying it for outdoors. So we come up with this very fascinating
idea of רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir which is wild, which he tried
to limit somewhat. And we use that to explain one roof to
the other and it's not really because it's a different domain, it's
because it's this concern about, you know, coming to confuse it in
a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim scenario. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: והרי כותל, v'harei kosel, the גמרא Gemara is not necessarily
buying in that this is a real issue, this idea that you
can't put stuff on pillars in רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid, והרי כותל,
v'harei kosel, how about the wall שבין בתי חצרות, shebein basei chatzeiros,
between two courtyards? Now remember we had this case of a wall
between two courtyards, right, and the question was did they make an
עירוב or not make an עירוב, can they use the wall or
not use the wall, but the whole discussion was an עירוב discussion.
Nobody ever said that in principle you cannot put from your yard
onto the top of a wall. Right? According to רבי מאיר, Rebbi
Meir you wouldn't be allowed to do that. Put from your yard
onto the top of a wall, you know, even if there's nobody
else who's using the wall because that's your pillar in a רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid, So let's take a look. How about the wall
between two courtyards דקבוע, de-kavu'a, it's a fixed, it's a fixed
location? ואמר רבי יהודה, v'amar Rebbi Yehuda, says
רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, כשתמצא לומר לדברי רבי מאיר, k'she-timtza lomar l'divrei
Rebbi Meir, you will see גגין רשות לעצמן, gagin reshus l'atzman, חצרות
רשות לעצמן, chatzeiros reshus l'atzman, קרפיפות רשות לעצמן. karpifos reshus l'atzman. So
the first thing we want to clarify, which is not clear in
the משנה, and this is unrelated to this whole discussion of pillars
in רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, is that as we said, רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon. says you can go from a חצר chatzer to a
גג, gag you know, here, not to the house itself. You can
go from a חצר chatzer, to the rooftop, right, and from the
rooftop to a קרפף. karpaf, He says that they're all one single
רשות. Okay. That is, you know, that's רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon Let's
just draw this a little bit. Let's try and make this a
little
bit clearer. Okay. So you've got your, you've got your houses in
your
חצר, chatzer. okay, and you've got your thing that starts here. So
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon, says you can go, you know, from this
courtyard, you know, you can go from that onto the rooftop and
from that rooftop into a קרפף, karpaf. you know, and from the
קרפף, karpaf I don't know, back into another חצר. chatzer Okay. He
says that they're all the single one רשות. And we know that
רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon excuse me, that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says
that the roof you can go from one rooftop to another rooftop,
right? That's what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says. You can go from
one rooftop to another rooftop. Would רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir say... so
presumably where he disagrees with רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is he'd say
you can't go from the rooftop to the yard and you can't
go from the yard to the קרפף. karpaf Those are distinct. But
what about one yard to the next? Would the same way he
said you can go from rooftop to rooftop, would רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir allow you to go from one courtyard to courtyard to courtyard
or from one קרפף karpaf? to קרפף karpaf to קרפף? karpef Would
he at least say that
those even if they're distinct from the roof, that they are their
own categories? So that's the first thing the גמרא Gemara is saying,
that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir, says rooftops are one category, קרפף is
one category, חצרות chatzeros are one category, and within that one category
you can carry. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says all three combined are
one category. Okay, so that's first of all is helpful in understanding
the parameters of the debate. But now how is this relevant for
this issue about the pillar? So let's take a look.
So having said that, that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir, says all rooftops
are one, all courtyards are one, etc. ואמר רבי יהודה, v'amar Rebbi
Yehuda, okay, so קרפיפות רשות לעצמן. karpifos reshus l'atzman. מאי לאו דשרי
ליה לטלטולי דרך כותל? mai lav deshary lei letiltulei derech kosel? So
here's what the גמרא Gemara says. The גמרא Gemara says if all
courtyards are one according to רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, so how are
you going to carry from one courtyard to the next? What's the
case of רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir here you have חצר chatzer A
and חצר chatzer B and you're going to carry from one courtyard
to the next? How are you going to carry? You're not going
to go out into the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, right? You have
to go straight from courtyard to courtyard. So how are you going
to go from courtyard to courtyard? Presumably the way you're going to
go from courtyard to courtyard is, and this involves the wall, is
you're going to go ahead and put it on the wall and
then walk around here or have your friend over there take it
from the wall and bring it down. So you see you can
use a wall, you can use a pillar, that's the גמרא's Gemara
proof, and the גמרא Gemara, answers, no, there's another way you can
go straight from one courtyard to the courtyard. It says אמר רב
הונא בר יהודה אמר רב ששת Amar Rav Huna bar Yehuda amar
Rav Sheshes לא להכניס ולהוציא דרך פתחים. lo lehachnis ulehotzi derech p'tachim.
What, you never heard of a hole in the wall? You never
heard of a little door in the wall? So you don't have
to go over the, you don't have to use the wall. There
can be a doorway here and you could just walk it through
the doorway. So you can now prove maybe all the discussion we
had in the last פרק about putting stuff on the top of
the wall and what if courtyards are competing for the wall? The
גמרא's Gemara saying according to רבי מאיר, forget competing. You could never
use the wall. You cannot use pillars and like רשות היחיד in
the middle of רשות היחיד. Okay, so it is a, we don't
פסקן pasken that way obviously, okay, but it is a very radical
position of limiting the use in a רשות היחיד. And that's what
the גמרא Gemara, draws on to explain the idea of different leveled
roofs. All right, now we go back to the חכמים. Chachamim So
what do we have though? We have three positions, okay? Our three
positions are
רבי מאיר that
says all גגות gagos are all one, and then the גמרא Gemara
clarifies the same way גגות gagos are one, right, קרפף is all
one and חצר is all one, but these are all different from
one another. We have רבי שמעון that says גג קרפף וחצר gag
karpef vechatzer are all one big category and they're one, go from
one property to the other. And then we have the חכמים Chachamim
who at least say that by the rooftops, the גגות gagos are
each one is different. Okay, now they might not say that by
these cases קרפף וחצר karpef vechatzer because קרפף וחצר karpef vechatzer are
all basically communal spaces, right? Not public, but communal for the people
for who owns them. So these they might agree all קרפפות karpefos
are one or all חצרות are one. But the גגות gagos, is
actually more distinct because they are the tops of buildings that below
them are distinct units. So the חכמים Chachamim. say at least for
the גגות, those remain distinct units from one another. And now we're
going to look at the parameters of the position of
the
חכמים. Chachamim? Okay. חכמים אומרים כל אחת ואחת רשות בפני עצמה. Chachamim
omrim kol achas ve'achas reshus bifnei atzma. איתמר Ismar רב אמר אין
מטלטלין בו אלא בארבע אמות. Rav amar ein m'talt'lin bo ela be'arba
amos. How about using the rooftop itself according to the חכמים? chachamim
So רב Rav says you can only use it within ארבע אמות.
arba amos. The rooftop is basically אסור to carry even on the
rooftop, one rooftop. ושמואל אמר מותר לטלטל בכולו. Ushmuel amar mutar letaltel
bekulo. We'll talk because why? And שמואל Shmuel says it's allowed because
there's a basic הלכה halacha about called,
which we you might remember this from before, פרוץ במילואו למקום האסור
לו. parutz bemilo'o lemakom ha'assur lo.
Okay,
which is, is that if you have a domain which in itself
is okay, but it's completely open on one side to a domain
that is forbidden, then that sort of makes itself felt and you
can't even carry in the domain that's okay. And therefore comes along
רב Rav and says what do you have in this case? What
you have is if you've got one rooftop and another, so if
we'll assume we're looking here at the at the tops of the
roofs, I mean down here's whatever, but you have one rooftop and
another and this is roof A because of building A and this
is roof B. So even though this is technically okay and each
one is okay in its own terms because it's its own רשות
היחיד, right? It has four walls and so on. But he says
but look, it's completely exposed to a space that it can't carry
into. What if, so if one side of it is completely open
to a space that it can't carry into, that makes this side
for, that makes that רשות forbidden as well. So since you can't
carry from A to B and it's completely open into B, there's
no even beginning of a מחיצה mechitzah between A and B, then
you cannot carry in A itself. Okay, so that's what he says
and שמואל Shmuel disagrees. So let's try to understand why שמואל Shmuel
disagrees, if שמואל Shmuel buys into that principle and what the debate
is about. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
במחיצות הניכרות, bimchitzos hanikaros, if the walls are visible or evident, דכולי
עלמא לא פליגי, decholay alma lo peligi, they don't, nobody argues that
that's okay. So the question here is attached or detached buildings. If
you have detached buildings, right, then your rooftops look like this. Okay,
it's not considered exposed. Why is A not exposed to B? And
it's not because even if they're like even if they're like an
inch apart, it's not because it's like you have to make a
big jump from A to B. It's not exposed to B because
you can see the wall of A. And since you can see
this wall down here, we can as if visually see it as
if it's up here and it's clearly distinct. It's not considered exposed
to B because the wall of the separate A and B and
B and A because B has its own wall is visible below.
So that's what makes it as if it's visible above and that
makes it not less considered exposed.
Isn't it a wall though? It's not it's open visually but
the Let's even assume that this is within four טפחים, tefachim, let's
assume it's within three טפחים. tefachim. Even if הלכתית halachically it's considered
contiguous,
right?
That would be a gap for the principle of פרץ במלואו. parutz
bimlo'o.
Right. So exactly, right. Something that would not be a gap for
פרץ במלואו, parutz bimlo'o, even if the gap is so small that
it's still considered exposed and accessible and contiguous, the existence of a
visible wall creates the division. So if the wall is visible, everybody
agrees you're it's okay.
פליגי, Pligi, what's the debate? במחיצות שאינם ניכרות. B'mechitzot she'einam nikarot. They're
attached houses. So the wall below that would divide them above and
make it not considered פרץ במלואו parutz bimlo'o is completely invisible. And
therefore does it do the job of dividing them? רב אמר, Rav
amar, אין מטלטלין בו אלא בארבע אמות, ein metalatelin bo ela b'arba
amot, לא אמרינן גוד אסיק מחיצתא. lo amrinan gud asik mechitzta. You
don't say the wall should extend upwards. Now רש"י Rashi, says, if
you look at little רש"י, Rashi the last line on the גמרא,
Gemara לא אמרינן גוד אסיק מחיצתא בכי האי גוונא, lo amrinan gud
asik mechitzta b'hai gavna, right? Which just shows you what you can
say in three words. רש"י is saying it's not saying that he
denies גוד אסיק, gud asik, because he would still agree that the
wall would be considered to continue up and make the roof a
רשות היחיד, right? It's just that it doesn't go up enough. Meaning
this wall certainly does consider to go up to make this a
רשות היחיד, but because it's invisible below, it doesn't do enough of
a job of being a wall to separate it from B. That's
רב's Rav position. ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel amar, and שמואל Shmuel says,
מותר לטלטל בכולו, mutar letaltel b'kulo, אמרינן גוד אסיק מחיצתא. amrinan gud
asik mechitzta. No, the fact that you have this imaginary wall extending
up, even if it's an invisible and imaginary wall, it's enough to
separate A from B.
And always when they did make an עירוב, if they did make
an עירוב and everyone says you can go from a גג to
the,
oh, they did not make an עירוב. Yeah, they did not make
an עירוב. Exactly. Sure, because you can go from house A to
house B. תנן. Tnan. Okay, so let's try to see if we
can try to get prove one side or other of the רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel debate. וחכמים אומרים כל אחד ואחד רשות לעצמו.
V'chachamim omrim kol echad v'echad reshut l'atzmo. וחכמים say every every roof
is its own domain. So if I just said that to you,
what would you say is the implication? Can you carry in one
roof by itself?
Yes, only in itself.
Yes, every roof is its own domain. Don't go from one to
the other, but within one you're fine. So that seems to be
שמואל. Shmuel. So the גמרא says, בשלמא לשמואל ניחא. Bishlama l'Shmuel nicha.
For שמואל Shmuel that's fine. אלא לרב קשיא. Ela l'Rav kashya. For
רב Rav, it's difficult because it sounds like you can carry on
each individual rooftop. So אמרי דבי רב משמיה דרב. Amri d'bei Rav
mishmeih d'Rav. So from the ישיבה yeshiva of רב, Rav, they said
in the name of רב, Rav שלא יטלטל בו אלא ארבע אמות
בגג זה וארבע אמות בגג זה. shelo yetaltel bo ela arba amot
b'gag zeh v'arba amot b'gag zeh. No, we're talking about moving less
than four אמות. amot. So what we mean is you want to
move just four אמות. amot. Or you cannot move four אמות amot
from A to B. You can move four אמות amot within A,
but you cannot move four אמות amot from A to B. So
basically, no, it does not mean that you can carry as much
as you want within A. It means you can carry four אמות
amot within A. But even if you're only doing four אמות, amot,
you still can't cross the threshold from A to B. Alright? So
the basic answer, you're looking confused.
The basic answer is: No, you can't carry four אמות amot in
A. You can never go from A to B even if you're
only taking one step, and but you can go a little bit
in A, you can go four אמות, amot, but you really can't
carry in A. Okay, and certainly not as much as you want.
והא אמר רב אלעזר, V'ha amar Rav Elazar, says the גמרא, כי
הוינן בבבל, ki havinnan b'Vavel,
when I was in בבל, Bavel, הוי
אמרינן דבי רב משמיה דרב אמרו, havay amrinan d'bei Rav mishmeih d'Rav
amru, they said that the house of רב Rav in the name
of רב Rav. said, אין מטלטלין בו אלא בארבע אמות, ein metalatelin
bo ela b'arba amot, that you can only carry four אמות amot
on each rooftop individually. והני דבי שמואל תנו. V'hanei d'bei Shmuel tanu.
So so far we're repeating what we said. And those of the
house of שמואל Shmuel taught, אין להן אלא גגן, ein lahen ela
gagan,
that they had a ברייתא braita that said according to the חכמים
Chachamim that they had, the people of A can only use the
roof of A. So again, that sounds like they have unlimited use
at least of their own rooftop. So מאי אין להן אלא גגן?
Mai ein lahen ela gagan? What does that mean, that they have
that they only have the use of their roof of their rooftop?
לאו דשרי לטלטולי בכוליה? Lav d'sharei l'taltulei b'kulei? Doesn't that suggest that
they can carry completely on their own rooftop? So the גמרא says
back, ומי אלימא ממתניתין? U'mi alima m'matnitin?
That's not any stronger of a proof than the language of our
משנה. דאוקימנא שלא יטלטל שתי אמות בגג זה ושתי אמות בגג זה.
D'okimna shelo yetaltel shtei amot b'gag zeh v'shtei amot b'gag zeh. That
we said the משנה means you can't do even do one step,
two אמות amot here, two אמות amot there, one step from A
to B, and you can do four אמות amot within A. We
don't mean
you can do without reservations within A. We mean within A at
least you're able to go four אמות. amot. ושמואל סבר נמי לכוליה.
U'Shmuel
savar nami l'kuleih.
Okay, but this is defending רב. Rav הכא נמי שתי אמות בגג
זה ושתי אמות בגג זה. Hacha nami shtei amot b'gag zeh v'shtei
amot b'gag zeh. Okay. So basically what we're saying is the simple
text obviously suggests that
you have at least your own rooftop without reservations. But the גמרא
says maybe it just means on your own rooftop at least you
get four אמות, amot, but going from A to B is categorically
forbidden. Okay, and certainly not as much as you want. אמר רב
יוסף Rav Yosef *Amar Rav Yosef*, said רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav
Yosef*, לא שמיע לי השמעתא *lo shemia li hashmata*. I guess you
know it's so interesting you know particularly in a given מסכת *Masechet*,
right we have seen a lot in עירובין *Eruvin* of רב יוסף
Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* A talking in general, like this interesting in
general to know the different concentrations of different אמוראים *Amoraim* in the
different מסכתות *Masechtot*. Some of them clearly invested more in one area
than in another. So and in so we get a lot of
רב יוסף Rav Yosef, *Rav Yosef*, we get a lot of him
having forgotten and being reminded, those scenarios come up a lot in
עירובין *Eruvin*. So רב Rav יוסף *Rav Yosef* said, you know, I
never heard this discussion about רב Rav *Rav* and שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*
and whatever, so אמר ליה אביי Abaye *amar leh Abaye*, אביי *Abaye*
said to him, את אמרתנה ניהלן *at amartena nialan*. What do you
mean? You you taught us this, והא אמרתנה ניהלן *veha amartena nialan*,
and you said it in the context of the following of the
following teaching. גג גדול הסמוך לקטן *Gag gadol hasamuch lakatam*, if you
have a big roof next to a small roof, הגדול מותר והקטן
אסור *hagadol mutar vehakatan asur*. The big is permitted, the small is
forbidden. What does that mean?
It means, let's say they're
not separate, they are attached, but they are different sizes. One you
have a big building, and here you have a small building. Okay,
they're at so,
it might be that they're attached, but at least down here for
the extended part you have a visible wall. You don't have a
visible wall for the connection, but you have a visible wall for
the extended part. And in that scenario the big one is okay
and the small one is forbidden. Why is the big one okay
and the small one forbidden?
The big one okay what the whole in its entirety?
You can carry within A, but you cannot carry within B.
B is completely open,
B is פרוץ במילואו *parutz bimlo'o*. B has complete you do not
consider this a מחיצה mechitza *mechitza*, it's not visible. This you do
consider a מחיצה mechitza, *mechitza*, it is visible. So B is completely
exposed and A is not completely exposed, A is to some degree
a partial wall with an opening. So A is is okay, it's
distinct, but B is completely undifferentiated and therefore B is forbidden. Now
that would seem to support רב Rav *Rav*'s position, that in principle
the non-visible part is not considered a wall. Right, and it's only
okay here because part a part of this is visible where it
extends beyond. So let's take a look.
So רב Rav *Rav* would say that that the גדול *gadol* is
מותר *mutar* because of the four אמות *amot*? No, no, no, no,
this is good for רב Rav *Rav*. The גדול *gadol* is מותר
*mutar* because he has a partial wall. It's in principle right רב
Rav, *Rav* and שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* don't agree disagree when it's visible
below. So this actually is completely supports רב Rav *Rav*, because this
makes it clear that this part is not considered a wall. And
that's basically רב Rav *Rav*'s position and that's why B is אסור
*asur*. A is only מותר *mutar* because it's visible, but when you
but this, that's not considered a wall at all and that is
actually רב *Rav*'s position. So that was the initial teaching, okay, הגדול
מותר והקטן אסור *hagadol mutar vehakatan asur*. Now והא אמרת לן עלה
*veha amarta lan ala*, and you said to us that there was
actually שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* interprets that in a different way. So again,
this is good according to רב *Rav*, and here's how שמואל Shmuel,
*Shmuel*'s going to interpret it. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Shmuel *Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel*, so said רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* in the
name of שמואל Shmuel. *Shmuel*, לא שנו אלא שיש דיורין על זה
ודיורין על זה *lo shanu ella sheyesh diurin al zeh vediurin al
zeh*. That's only true if people are actually living on the roof,
דהוה ליה דהאי קטן מחיצה mechitza, הנדרסת *dehavei leh dehai katan mechitza
nidreset*. That then the the the separation is considered a non-separation because
people actually trample over it. אבל אין דיורין על זה ועל זה
שניהם מותרין *aval ein diurin al zeh veal zeh shneihem mutarin*, but
if people aren't living on it, then they're both permissible. So what
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says is, do people see why this is case
is prima facie evidence for רב *Rav*? because it basically assumes that
this place where they're connected doesn't serve as a wall. So said
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*, that's only when people actually regularly use the roof
and regularly walk over this line. And since people regularly walk over
that line, so it's not just invisible but it's sort of shown
to be invisible. It's like the emperor's new clothes. Okay, that actually
people are constantly crossing that and basically demonstrating that it's not a
boundary. So in that case I agree to רב *Rav*. In that
case I agree that that does not serve to differentiate the רשויות
*reshuyot* and so on, when it actually is regularly walked over. But
if basically the roofs are generally not used and this line is
not violated on a regular basis, then actually I would say that
B is also okay, that's my position. So does this type of
a line between the two places when not visible below, is it
considered a מחיצה mechitza *mechitza*? רב *Rav* says no and that's why
this is a problem, שמואל *Shmuel* says yes and the only and
in a normal case this actually would be okay. The only reason
it's a problem is a special case that people are constantly walking
over the line. Okay but the and now the point that אביי
*Abaye* is making back to רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* is, so that's
the context in which you taught us this debate of רב *Rav*
and שמואל *Shmuel*, that רב *Rav* would say it's it's never okay
and שמואל *Shmuel* says it's only not okay if people are walking
over it. All right, so let's take a look where the גמרא
*Gemara* goes. אמר ליה *amar
leh* So רב יוסף said back to him, No, no, no, no,
no. Actually, maybe אביי was helping him remember what he said. And
he says, No, that's not what I said to you about this.
אנא הכי אמרי לכו. Ana hachi amri lechu. This is what I
said to you about this issue about the big roof and the
small roof.
לא שנו אלא שיש מחיצה על זה ומחיצה על זה.
Lo shanu ela sheyesh
mechitza al zeh umechitza al zeh. דגדול משתרי בגיפופי וקטן נפרץ במילואו.
De-gadol mishtari be-gifufei ve-katan nifrat bimlo'o. I actually said that where that
we're talking about there's actually a actual fence around it. That that
again, now he's maybe consistently afraid of not debating the רב and
שמואל debate, but I did not say the point about to read
it in as you did to read it as the question about
whether the line is being stepped over. The fact that this line
is considered to be a pro-, you know, the fact I'm sorry,
let's take a look. He says, so first to start the idea
about why this roof hop is okay. We've assumed that this roof
top is okay because everybody agrees the visible part extends upwards, right?
That's not debated between רב and שמואל, the visible part.
What רב יוסף is saying is, no, actually I never said such
a thing. And I actually said that we're talking about actually, there's
a real מחיצה mechitza, around it. And that it's not because of
down here. So this is much more מחמיר machmir because we said
that רב and שמואל both agree that down here works. רב יוסף
says the only reason A is okay is that there's actually a
is that there's actually, you know,
each one actually has a fence around its own domain. Okay, so
let's take a look. So he says,
what?
Right, at first he doesn't remember.
Right. And then he then his memory maybe he jogged his memory
a little bit.
And everyone else remembers him saying this and
well, so far it was אביי remembered. And at the end of
the day, maybe it doesn't matter what he actually said because now
at least he's telling us what he actually believes at least. And
now actually he's articulating, so in the end did it really matter
whether he said it or not? I mean, this is הלכה
למעשה, halacha le-ma'aseh, he said it. Okay and they heard him say
it, they understood it, they acted.
Right, right. Correct, right. They're not arguing about somebody doing something wrong,
we're just talking theoretically here and he's articulating a different position.
But it's not a theoretical הלכה.
halacha. I know! But he's entitled to have a position, whether he
accurately said this before or didn't. Presumably he's saying, 'Yeah, presumably he's
saying if I said anything I must have said this.' I do
that all the time, because I always forget what I said. But
then I know what I think right now, so I
assume that must have been what I said before.
Except
I don't before he got sick?
אביי has a legitimate position. Every, yeah, all of those are legitimate
positions, because it's not that a particular historical reality determines the הלכה.
halacha. Right now, this is his position.
But אביי is saying you didn't understand it correctly.
He is saying that, but in the end that's not what matters.
Let's let's go further, okay? So the גמרא says like this: לא
שנו אלא שיש מחיצה על זה ומחיצה על זה. Lo shanu ela
she-yesh mechitza al zeh u-mechitza al zeh. If I talked about that
case, here's what I said to you. I said actually more מחמיר
machmir than רב and שמואל, that it only works that A is
okay if there actually is a wall around A. דגדול משתרי בגיפופי,
De-gadol mishtari be-gifufei, the big one is permissible by גיפופי gifufei which
is like the partial, you know, walls that leave this opening in
the middle. וקטן נפרץ במילואו, Ve-katan nifrat bimlo'o, and the smaller one
is completely exposed. אבל אין מחיצה לא לזה ולא לזה, Aval ein
mechitza lo le-zeh velo le-zeh, but if there's no real wall, שניהם
אסורין, sheneihem asurin, that they're both forbidden. Okay, so actually he says,
you know what, I didn't tell you the שמואל position and walking
over the line. I actually said that you need a real מחיצה,
mechitza. even more מחמיר machmir than רב if you want to make
them separate domains. So now אביי isn't taking this line down. אביי
says like Rifka says, you're not going to tell me what I
heard. אביי says, והדיירין אמרת לן, Ve-ha-diyyarin amarta lan, no,
I remember you told us that it matters about like people dwelling
up there. And I remember and the way I I remember it
is is that therefore it mattered about whether they were violating that
line and stepping over it. You didn't tell us oh it's oh
by the way there are מחיצות. mechitzot, What the idea you introduced
was the question about whether people are using the space above and
stepping over the line or not. So now he says back, אי
אמרי לכו דיירין, i amri lechu diyyarin, you know what, if I
mentioned the idea of people living up there, it's not what you're
saying I said. Here's what I must have been been talking about.
הכי אמרי לכו. Hachi amri lechu. I gotta tell you this is
nice because normally רב יוסף is very passive. I don't remember, oh
here's what you told us, go on. Here he's like a little
bit like you know he's a little more sprightly. He's saying, no,
no, no, no, no, now you know this must be what I
said to you. So if I mentioned the idea of people living...
I don't know. הכי אמרי לכו, Hachi amri lechu, this is what
I said to you. לא שנו אלא שיש מחיצה ראויה לדירה על
זה ומחיצה ראויה לדירה על זה. Lo shanu ela sheyesh mechitza re'uya
le-dira al zeh u-mechitza re'uya le-dira al zeh.
That it has to be A, I can stick by my guns,
that it has to be a real מחיצה, mechitza you don't use
the space below. Plus it has to be a מחיצה mechitza that
is fit for for
for inhabiting. I'll tell you see what that means in a minute.
דגדול משתרי בגיפופי, De-gadol mishtari be-gifufei, that
the top one is allowed because... the partial wall. הקטן נפרץ במילואו,
hakatan nifratz b'miluo, and the smaller one is totally exposed.
אבל יש מחיצה ראויה לדירה על הגדול, aval yesh mechitza reuya l'dirah
al hagadol,
but if it's fit for habitation, which I'll say in a minute
what it means, on the top one, ואין ראויה לדירה על הקטן,
v'ein reuya l'dirah al hakatan, but it's not fit for habitation on
the lower one, אפילו קטן שרי לבני גדול, afilu katan shari livnei
gadol, even the lower one is permissible. So let me just tell
you what this means.
So basically ראויה לדירה reuya l'dirah means that you've got a wall
that is really a constructed wall, that if you wanted to, you
could decide to move to the rooftop, maybe you'd have to put
on a roof, but you could decide to move to the rooftop.
If you've got a permanent wall. לא ראויה לדירה lo reuya l'dirah
is basically, you know, you spread a curtain, okay? You know, you
did something that halachically is a מחיצה, mechitza, but it's not really
part of, you know, the construct, you know, part of the configuration.
So what he says is A, I'm insisting that I'm being more
מחמיר machmir than Rav and Shmuel, and I am saying that A
is only allowed with a real מחיצה. mechitza The fact that it's
visible below doesn't help. But here's what I'll be lenient about this
issue about whether there are people living there. Not really people living
there and crossing the boundaries like you were talking about, but whether,
but the מחיצה mechitzah on B, if B's מחיצה in this case
A is okay within A, B is not good, and A can't
carry in B because B is a distinct domain, you can't go
from one to the other. But he says, let's say they don't
put up real walls here. Let's say the walls here are more,
you know, like, like, like, you know, technically they're walls, but they're
not serious walls, you know, they're like a curtain. So in that
case A, not only is A allowed and B can't carry, A
can even carry into B. Why is that? Because why can't A
carry into B? Because B is considered separate because different people live
in it. But in reality nobody really lives on the roof. So
A, by making permanent מחיצות, has made it like they really live
on the roof. B has effectively, by making impermanent, made it clear
that they don't live on the roof, and they certainly don't live
on the roof as much as A does. So this, so B
stops being a separate domain up here because it's, because of its,
you know, because of the contrast to the way A has really
taken a presence up on the roof. And therefore to actually, you
can, A can actually go from A to B. Let's just read
this. B still can obviously cannot because it's completely not their domain.
Okay, אבל יש מחיצה ראויה לדירה על הגדול, aval yesh mechitza reuya
l'dirah al hagadol, if A has a serious מחיצה, ואין ראויה לדירה
על הקטן, v'ein reuya l'dirah al hakatan, and B, they might have
a halachic מחיצה but it's not clear they're living up on the
roof, אפילו קטן שרי לבני גדול, afilu katan shari livnei gadol, then
B is even allowed to, A can even go into B, carry
into B. מאי טעמא, what's the reason? כיון דלא עבד מחיצה, keivan
d'lo avad mechitza, since they didn't make a real wall, a wall
fit for inhabiting, סלוקי סליקי נפשיה מהכא, siluki silikei nafshei meihacha, they
have effectively removed their presence from here. Meaning, so the same way
Rabbi Meir says there really isn't a presence of different owners on
the rooftop, he's saying the חכמים Chachamim, who say there is the
presence of different owners, and therefore you have problems from one rooftop
to the other, will admit there are some cases that it could
be like there isn't a presence, especially by the contrast. A has
made it clear that they're living up here, B has made it
clear they're not living up here, and that's therefore from A's perspective
they can move to B. I'm not saying they can't use their
rooftop.
Even though they're different owners, right.
So, כהא
דאמר רב נחמן, keha d'amar Rav Nachman, like רב נחמן Rav Nachman
said, עשו סולם קבוע לגגו, הותר בכל הגגין כולן. asu sulam kavua
l'gago, hutar b'chol hagagin kulan. So it's a very interesting thing. He
says for according to Rabbi Meir, according to, excuse me, the חכמים,
Chachamim. that you can't go from one rooftop to the other, right,
all these rooftops are considered to be distinct because they're distinct below,
okay? But he says actually, I have a way that I can
go ahead and use all the rooftops, right? Why? Because they're distinct
because since different people own them below, it's like they're different ownerships
up top. But we all know that people aren't really using them
so much at the top, but it's, you know, it's a virtual
A and it's a virtual B, it's a quasi A and it's
a quasi B. If I go ahead and I make a ladder
to my rooftop, then I've turned my quasi A into a real
A. And therefore that trumps all of these quasis. And therefore because
I have really established my presence here, and your presence here is
much more partial and virtual, I actually can make total use of
all of that. But you guys can't, but I can. Okay? Because
from the position of somebody who really lives here, other, you guys
don't live here, okay? So therefore you're not considered to be a
presence from the position of really living here when I make a
ladder. Let's just, let me just read that. This is all according
to the חכמים. Chachamim Okay, הותר בכל הגגין כולן. hutar b'chol hagagin
kulan. You know,
that's where we'll end for today. So Dov, you had a question
before and then no, no, any last questions?
But each person can still go up to their own roof at
any time?
In this case, can B go onto their own roof? Yes, that
is
true. Except for the question of נפרץ במילואו למקום האסור לו. nifratz
b'miluo l'makom ha'asur lo. Whether B can use their own roof would
be the debate of רב and שמואל. So let me just end
by saying and then take other questions after to just sum it
up that basically, according to the חכמים Chachamim. that the roofs are
different domains, are they considered separate enough that you can use each
domain separately? So according to רב, and רב and שמואל both agree
that if it's not attached or if it's extending beyond and it's
visible below, that's enough to make it considered distinct. But if they're
completely attached, that's a debate of רב and שמואל whether you can
use individual roof. And רב יוסף, now at least in what he's
saying here, what he's remembering, whether it's actually what he said or
not, is actually being more מחמיר machmir and saying I don't even
accept it even when it's visible below. If I'm going to want
a roof to be distinct, it's going to have to have a
real מחיצה around it, all according to the חכמים. But the one
big leniency that we've now introduced is if you establish real habitation
above by walls or by a ladder or whatever, that trumps all
of these quasi and that gives you total total rights and total
control. Okay, so more of this fun discussion tomorrow.